<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Domain Names on The Witty Ginger</title>
    <link>https://dtanner.github.io/categories/domain-names/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Domain Names on The Witty Ginger</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://dtanner.github.io/categories/domain-names/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Domain names for daughters</title>
      <link>https://dtanner.github.io/post/domain-names-for-daughters/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://dtanner.github.io/post/domain-names-for-daughters/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Though the biggest domain name purchases are probably long-gone since the initial dot-com boom, they still remain a valued property. They&amp;rsquo;ll never be as valuable as real land of course, since we can always create more of them, as opposed to things like lake-front property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent mad rush for facebook profile names reminded me of this new global scale of gold rush activity. And yes, I&amp;rsquo;m a little annoyed that someone that has been farming this interweb as long as I have was offered a name like dan.tanner2 (in my day, we used Mosiac. And we liked it!). It also reminded me of something I&amp;rsquo;m hoping will come in handy for my two daughters some day - their very own short and memorable domain names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding a decent available domain name is a tenaciously difficult PITA. It&amp;rsquo;s an exercise in creativity and luck, and girls names are especially tough. Not only do you have to wrestle with the general lack of availability, but also the likelihood that they&amp;rsquo;ll change their name when they get married. In my case, that&amp;rsquo;s sometime after age 28, when they&amp;rsquo;ve agreed to start dating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, my girls are named Maria Mae and Daniela Teresa. All good variants of maria and daniela were taken, which would&amp;rsquo;ve been ideal. And no last names were considered because of the potential marriage name change. After tinkering around for a while, here&amp;rsquo;s what I ended up saving for them:
mariamae.com and danielat.com
They&amp;rsquo;re both fairly mnemonic, and they&amp;rsquo;re both flexible enough to last. And they&amp;rsquo;re both shorter than my domain name!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;ll be a few years, but hopefully they&amp;rsquo;ll be useful. Not to mention give me a little boost in the cool dad category. Not that I&amp;rsquo;ll need any help in that category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now&amp;hellip;where did my favorite plaid pants go?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>